Guide to the Brenda and Alice Heyl Kiessling Medical School notebooks, 1924-1970 MS2401
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Brenda and Alice Heyl Kiessling Medical School notebooks
1924-1970
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Kiessling, Brenda, Doctor
MS2401
2 Linear Feet
Alice Heyl Kiessling and daughter Brenda Kiessling both received medical degrees from George Washington University. Alice graduated in 1929 and worked as a psychiatrist in Arlington, Virginia. Brenda is a 1972 graduate who practices Family Medicine in Falls Church, Virginia. The collection documents their experience as medical school students. The materials include course notes and a published work, and date from 1924-1970.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Brenda Kiessling, 2022 April 5 (2022.020).
Scope and Contents
This collection contains medical school notes and a published work. The materials date from 1924 to 1970.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Collection is ordered chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
Alice Heyl Kiessling (1903-1955) received an A.B. from Cornell University in 1925 and a medical degree from George Washington University in 1929. During her time at George Washington University, she was involved with Kappa Alpha Theta and Alpha Epsilon Iota and served a term as class treasurer. Following graduation, she specialized in psychiatry and became head of the Department of Psychiatry at Arlington Hospital in the 1950s. Dr. Kiesling also served as chair of the mental health and hospital committees for the Fairfax Medical Society, published numerous articles in her field, and participated as an active member of the Washington Psychiatric Society. In honor of her considerable career achievements, the American Society of Psychoanalytic Physicians hosts a yearly lecture in her memorial.
Brenda Kiessling, daughter of Alice and Oscar Kiessling, received her B.A. from Oberlin College and graduated from the George Washington University School of Medicine in 1972. She practices Family Medicine in Falls Church, Virginia.
Medicine; Medical care; Women -- Education; George Washington University. School of Medicine; Kiessling, Brenda, Doctor; Kiessling, Brenda, Doctor; Kiessling, Alice Heyl, Doctor
- Alice Heyl Kiessling, 1924-1929; MS2401
  Arrangement
  Series is organized chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this series include the medical school notebooks of Alice Heyl Kiessling. They range in date from 1924-1929.
  - Notes - Volume I, 1924-1925; MS2401 Series 1 (Box 1, Item 1)
    General
    Contains notes from final years at Cornell University and initial time at George Washington University Medical School. Topics covered include: Anatomical Methods, Dr. Papez; Embryology of Vertabrates, Dr. Adelman; Histology, Dr. Kingsbury.
  - Notes - Volume II, 1926-1928; MS2401 Series 1 (Box 1, Item 2)
    Topics covered include: Pathology, Pathological Embryology, Neuro-Pathology, Pharmacology, Physical Diagnosis, Physiology, Preventative Medicine and Hygiene, Psychiatry, Therapeutics, Tropical Medicine, Roentgenology, and Surgery.
  - Notes - Volume III, 1925-1929; MS2401 Series 1 (Box 1, Item 3)
    Topics covered include: Anaesthesia, Anatomy, Neuro-Anatomy, Bacteriology, Biochemistry, Cardiology, Clinical Chemistry, Clinical Microscopy, Dermatology, Embryology of Vertabrates, Cenito-Urinary Surgery, and Syphilology.
- Brenda Kiessling, 1959-1970; MS2401
  Materials in this series include a published work and the medical school notebooks of Brenda Kiessling.
  - "A Brief Account of Henry Gray F.R.S. and his Anatomy", 1959; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1st Semester Fall 1968 GW Medical School, Brenda Kiessling (Completely Missing: Gross Anatomy) [1/2], 1968 August-1968 December; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1st Semester Fall 1968 GW Medical School, Brenda Kiessling (Completely Missing: Gross Anatomy) [2/2], 1968 August-1968 December; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2nd Semester (End 1st Year) Spring 1969, GW Medical School, Brenda Kiessling [1/2], 1969 January-1969 May; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 2nd Semester (End 1st Year) Spring 1969, GW Medical School, Brenda Kiessling [2/2], 1969 January-1969 May; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1st Semester - 2nd Year (3rd Semester) Fall 1969 Brenda Kiessling, GW Medical School & Some 4th Semester Materials [1/2], 1969 August-1970 May; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1st Semester - 2nd Year (3rd Semester) Fall 1969 Brenda Kiessling, GW Medical School & Some 4th Semester Materials [2/2], 1969 August-1969 December; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 4th Semester, 2nd Year, Spring 1970, GW Medical School, Brenda Kiessling [1/5], 1970 January-1970 May; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 4th Semester, 2nd Year, Spring 1970, GW Medical School, Brenda Kiessling [2/5], 1970 January-1970 May; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 4th Semester, 2nd Year, Spring 1970, GW Medical School, Brenda Kiessling [3/5], 1970 January-1970 May; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 4th Semester, 2nd Year, Spring 1970, GW Medical School, Brenda Kiessling [4/5], 1970 January-1970 May; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 4th Semester, 2nd Year, Spring 1970, GW Medical School, Brenda Kiessling [5/5], 1970 January-1970 May; MS2401 Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)